Granville, Mass. Granville Federated Church records, 1754-1941.
Congregational Library & Archives
Granville, Mass. Granville Federated Church records, 1754-1941.
RG5235
Congregational Library & Archives
1.09 Cubic Feet
(1 box)
The First Church of Christ in Granville was gathered in 1744, and Moses Tuttle was ordained as the first minister in 1747. The first meeting house was constructed during Tuttle's ministry. Timothy Mather Cooley, a Granville native, was called to become the minister of the First Church of Christ in 1795 and he served as the pastor for 63 years. In 1937, the First Church of Christ and the Baptist Church in Granville decided to share a building and merge to form the Granville Federated Church. This collection contains administrative records, membership records, and ministerial records and includes church records and meeting minutes, correspondence, disciplinary records, and relations of faith.
Cooley, Timothy Mather, 1772-1859
First Church of Christ (Granville, Mass.)
Granville Federated Church (Granville, Mass.)
Haynes, Lemuel, 1753-1833
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were loaned to the Congregational Library & Archives by the town of Granville, Massachusetts, in October 2014; 2014-82.
Digital Copies
Records within this collection were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions may be accessed online through our digital archive.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.
Historical Note
The town of Granville, Massachusetts, was first settled by English colonists in 1736. The town was incorporated in 1754. The First Church of Christ in Granville was gathered in 1744. Moses Tuttle was ordained as the first minister of the Church of Christ in 1747. The first meeting house was constructed during Tuttle's ministry and was made possible by a large financial contribution from Tuttle.
Numerous churches can trace their roots to the First Church of Christ in Granville. The West Granville Congregational Church, originally known as the Second or Middle Church of Granville, was gathered in 1781. The Tolland Congregational Church, originally known as the Third or West Church of Granville, was gathered in 1791. The Baptist Church in Granville was likewise formed in 1791. The Methodist Episcopal Church in Granville was formed in 1800.
Timothy Mather Cooley, a Granville native, was called to become the minister of the First Church of Christ in 1795, and he was ordained in 1796. During his ministry, in 1802, the second meeting house was constructed. Timothy Cooley served as minister of the church for more than 63 years and died in Granville on December 14, 1859.
In 1937, the First Church of Christ and the Baptist Church in Granville decided to share a building and merge to form the Granville Federated Church. The Granville Federated Church continues to serve the local community today.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains administrative records, membership records, and ministerial records from the Granville Federated Church. The collection includes administrative church records and meeting minutes, church correspondence, records of admissions and dismissions, church disciplinary records, confessions of faith and covenants, relations of faith, and ministerial correspondence.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into three series. Records within each series have been arranged chronologically, by start date, with closely related materials grouped together as appropriate.
Series 1: Church records, 1754-1941
Series 2: Membership records, 1756-1920
Series 3: Ministerial records, 1777-1870
Technical Requirements
To access digital materials on our digital archive, it is strongly recommended that you use the latest available version of Microsoft Edge, Google Chrome, Mozilla Firefox, or Safari (Apple).
Bibliography
Granville Jubilee. The First Church of Christ, Granville, Mass., August 28th, 1895. Pittsfield: Press of the Sun Printing Company, 1895. 17.11.1 G76.63 FirCC
Church discipline.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Clergy -- Correspondence.; Covenants (Church polity).; Creeds.; Experience (Religion).; New England's Hidden Histories.; Necrologies.; American Home Missionary Society; Cooley, Timothy Mather, 1772-1859; First Church of Christ (Granville, Mass.); Granville (Mass.) -- Church history.; Granville Federated Church (Granville, Mass.); Haynes, Lemuel, 1753-1833
- Church records, 1755 1941; 1754-1941; 15 Folders; 2 Items
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the administration of the Granville Federated Church. This series includes church administrative records and meeting minutes, church correspondence, financial records, programs and booklets, annual reports, and confessions of faith and covenants.
  - Church constitution and records, 1754, undated (Folder 2, Item 3-4)
  - Church records, 1755 1885; 1755-1885 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous church records, 1758 1857; 1758-1857 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ecclesiastical council records, 1761 1791; 1761-1791 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Church correspondence, 1769 1842; 1769-1842 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous church records, 1769 1856; 1769-1856 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Invitations to ecclesiastical councils, 1798 1853; 1798-1853 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Church records, 1802 1866; 1802-1866 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Financial records, 1825 1897; 1825-1897 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Programs, announcements, and printed materials, 1830 1868; 1830-1868 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "The church and the secession movement", 1856 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Home Missionary Society, 1883 1941; 1883-1884, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual meetings, 1901 1916; 1901-1916 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual church reports, 1903 1917; 1903-1917 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Confessions of faith and covenants, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Southwick emigrants, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Membership records, 1756 1920; 1756-1920; 21 Folders; 2 Items
  This series contains records and papers related to the members of Granville Federated Church. This series includes relations of faith, confessions and other disciplinary related documents, records of admissions and dismissions, and records of deaths.
  - Admissions and dismissions, 1756 1799; 1756-1799 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Admissions and dismissions, 1800 1849; 1800-1849 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Admissions and dismissions, 1850 1920; 1850-1920 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Confessions, 1758 1798; 1758-1798 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Confessions, 1800 1856; 1800-1856 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Church disciplinary records, 1758 1821; 1758-1821 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Deacon Hitchcock disciplinary case records, 1760 1770; 1760-1770 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Separatist disciplinary case records, 1762 1769; 1762-1769 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - James Burt disciplinary case records, 1763 1771; 1763-1771 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Relations, A-M, 1797 1846; 1797-1846 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Relations, O-Z, 1769 1847; 1769-1847 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Relations, 1800 1804; 1800-1804, undated (Folder 2, Item 1-2)
  - Experiences, 1798 1799; 1798-1799 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Mehitable Adams and Asa Seymor disciplinary case records, 1820 1821; 1820-1821 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Record of deaths, 1822 1866; 1822-1866 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Pledge of abstinence, 1827 1856; 1827-1856 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Cyrus Webster disciplinary case records, 1829 1833; 1829-1833 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Mr. Eno disciplinary case records, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Sunday school records, 1867 1907; 1867-1907 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Family dates and biographies, 1908, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Lucy A. Ward experience, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Fragmentary complaints, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Ministerial records, 1777 1870; 1777-1870; 9 Folders
  This series contains records relating to, or produced by, ministers. This series includes correspondence to and from ministers, ministers' copies of church records, records relating to the dismission of Rev. Smith, and manuscript sermons and essays.
  - Reverend Smith dismission, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Sermons and essays, 1790, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Lemuel Haynes correspondence, 1796 1810; 1796-1810 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Timothy Cooley correspondence, 1810 1856; 1810-1856 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Timothy Cooley's copies of church records, 1819 1833; 1819-1833 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Timothy Cooley correspondence, 1831 1857; 1831-1857 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Timothy Cooley correspondence with Henry W. Tryon, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Timothy Cooley correspondence regarding parsonage, 1855 1856; 1855-1856 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - A. E. Geike correspondence, 1858 1870; 1858-1870 (Box 1, Folder 45)